Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002
  - Treuhaft, Ben: Interview, 1996 September 4; cuid18096 (Box Digitized Access Files, Video ref37)
    This video contains footage from an interview with Ben Treuhaft, a piano tuner. He talks about his first trip to Cuba as part of Pam Montenegro's Freedom to Travel campaign, meeting Fidel Castro, and his later visits to Cuba. He describes his project sending donated pianos to Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:19.
  - Varela, Angel Fernandez: Interview, 1996 October 1; cuid18097 (Box 69, Cassette ref877, Box 84, Dvd ref877)
    Angel Fernandez Varela a teacher of Fidel Castro's who taught at the Belen Jesuit Preparatory School in Havana. An opponent of the Castro government, he was recruited by the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA). According to his son, Alvaro Fernandez, Valrela had been one of the CIA agents who secretly introduced among the Cuban population a false decree stating that they would lose parental authority, leading to Operation Peter Pan in the 1960s.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:06:54.
  - Varela, Angel Fernandez: Interview, 1996; cuid18098 (Box 69, Cassette ref878, Box 84, Dvd ref878)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:27:15.
  - Varela, Angel Fernandez: Interview, 1996; cuid369 (Box 95, Dvd ref988)
    In this portion of an interview Angel Fernandez Varela, Varela discusses the anti-Fidelista sentiment in Miami, and the way the opinions about Castro have changed in the Miami Cuban community. He suggests that anti-Fidelistas are still the majority in Miami, but those in favor of Castro are increasing. He addresses criticism of Castro as a dictator, and contends that he does not consider dictators frightening. He also discusses returning to Cuba in 1993. He describes meeting Castro again, and describes their meeting as amiable. In the second half of the interview Estela Bravo shares a yearbook from Colegio de Belén during the years when he was a teacher of Fidel Castro. Varela looks through the yearbook and shares stories about students and his memories at the school.
  - Walker, Alice: Interview, 1996 September 3; cuid18099 (Box 68, Cassette ref866, Box 84, Dvd ref866)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:16:34.
  - Walker, Alice: Interview (part 2), 1996 September 3; cuid370 (Box 62, Cassette ref1040, Box 96, Dvd ref1040)
    This video contains a segment of an interview with novelist Alice Walker. Walker begins with a discussion about Cuban education and efforts to spread literacy to the elderly. She also discusses her impressions of Cuba during various visits she took to the island. She discusses her first visit in 1978, and explains that she was dismayed by how many white men held positions of power and the government's treatment of gays. She later discusses meeting Fidel Castro on subsequent trips to Cuba with delegations brining medical supplies.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration 00:13:25.
  - Walker, Alice: Interview, 1996 September 3; cuid371 (Box 96, Dvd ref208)
    This video features part of an interview with author Alice Walker. Walker discusses her memories of Castro's 1995 speech at Riverside Church in Harlem, and her experience meeting Castro in person. She addresses American media portrayals of Castro as a dictator, which she says contrasts with her perception of him. Walker also discusses Castro's knowledge of agricultural issues, and concludes that his longevity as a leader in Cuba comes from the support he has from many Cuban citizens. The end of the video features still images of Walker with Castro and during her travels in Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:12:14
  - Walker, Alice: Interview, circa 1996; cuid372 (Box 86, Dvd ref36)
  - Walker, Alice: Interview, circa 1996; cuid373 (Box 86, Dvd ref26)
  - Walker, Lucius: Interview, 1996 August 1
    - Walker, Lucius: Interview Recording, 1996 August 1; cuid18100; 3 items This interview consists of 3 access DVDs (Box 75, Dvd ref12)
      The Rev. Lucius Walker, Jr. (1930-2010), a Baptist minister, founded Pastors for Peace. At the invitation of Fidel Castro in 2000, Rev. Walker formed and headed the committee that allowed US students from underserved communities to study medicine at the Latin American School of Medicine in Havana.
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 3 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:04:50; Part 2 - 00:01:27; Part 3 - 00:03:46.
    - Walker, Lucius: Interview Transcript, 1996 August 1; cuid18101
  - Walker, Lucius: Interview, 1996 August 1
    - Walker, Lucius: Interview Recording, 1996 August 1; cuid18102 (Box 75, Dvd ref16)
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:35.
    - Walker, Lucius: Interview Transcript, 1996 August 1; cuid18103
  - Walker, Lucius: Interview, 1996 August 1
    - Walker, Lucius: Interview Recording, 1996 August 1; cuid18104 (Box 75, Dvd ref17)
    - Walker, Lucius: Interview Transcript, 1996 August 1; cuid18105
  - Walker, Lucius: Caravan for Peace Press Conference (part 2), 1993 July 16; cuid18106 (Box 97, Dvd ref136)
    This video features a press conference with Baptist minister Lucius Walker and other representatives in support of the Caravan for Peace, which sought to deliver aid from the United States to Cuba. Walker and other speakers call for an end to the United States' blockade on Cuba, and express their hope that the caravan will ease the suffering of Cubans negatively impacted by the blockade. The end of this video features footage of protesters in Miami voicing their opposition to the Cuban government and the caravan.
  - Walker, Lucius: Caravan for Peace Press Conference (part 1), 1993 July 16; cuid18107 (Box 97, Dvd ref139)
    This video features a press conference in Miami announcing the departure of the second Caravan for Peace. The press conference features a statement by Baptist minister Lucius Walker, leader of Pastors for Peace who organized the caravan. Walker begins by celebrating the contributions of aid from Americans opposed to the US trade embargo against Cuba. Walker describes the extent of aid and provides some explanation the purpose of the aid and how it will be distributed. Also featured in the press conference is Andres Gomez of Antonio Maceo Brigades, which also participated in the caravan.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:27.
  - Birán Scenes, undated; cuid18108 (Box 98, Dvd ref1020)
    This video features footage of Fidel Castro's childhood home in Birán, Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:09:14.
  - Bosch/Aruca "Radio Progresso ECITVFAR", undated; cuid18109 (Box 9, Cassette ref46)
  - Brooklyn Academy of Music: Bravo and Steven Spielberg, 2002; TW_TAM_616_ER_5 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_5)
  - Brooklyn Academy of Music: Fidel Documentary Question and Answer, 2002; TW_TAM_616_ER_6 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_6)
  - Brooklyn Academy of Music: New York, 2002; TW_TAM_616_ER_7 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_7)
  - Castro, Fidel: Speaking, while having his portrait painted by Oswaldo Guayasamín, 1998 July; cuid18110 (Box 71, Cassette ref934, Box 85, Dvd ref934)
    In this footage, Fidel Castro is sitting for a portrait on his 70th birthday. This lengthy footage consists primarily of Castro speaking about a variety of subjects. It also features footage of news photographers, including Estela Bravo, to whom he appears to be speaking. He talks about his recent trip to the United States, describes an event where Yasser Arafat was asked to leave Lincoln Center, and talks about how he would have reacted if he been asked to leave. As the footage progresses, it is possible to see the progress of the portrait.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:34:00.
  - Castro, Fidel: Footage, Public Events, 2001 January 25; cuid374 (Box 96, Dvd ref1070)
    This video features clips of Fidel Castro at several public events filmed around the year 2000. The majority of the clips feature rallies and town meetings in Cuba calling for the return of Elian González. Castro does not speak in any of the clips, but can be seen greeting crowds. In one section he speaks to González's father Juan Miguel González Quintana, but cannot be heard due to poor audio quality. Other clips feature Castro touring a Cuban medical school with American reporter Andrea Mitchell, and clips included at the end of the tape feature Castro greeting crowds during his travels to other countries.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:32:12.
  - CBS News Archives Person to Person with Ed Murrow - "Fidel Castro", 1959 February 6; cuid18111 (Box 6, Cassette ref230)
  - Contact Lists, 2001; cuid18112 (Box 72, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 2002; cuid18113 (Box 72, Folder 3-4)
  - Flyers, circa 2001; cuid18114 (Box 72, Folder 16)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 1, Fidel addresses Parliament, 1998 September 4; cuid18115 (Box 70, Cassette ref923, Box 85, Dvd ref923)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:25.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 3, Fidel speaking at Parliament, 1998 September 4; cuid18116 (Box 70, Cassette ref924, Box 85, Dvd ref924)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: "Cape Town Interview - Parliament", 1998 September 4; cuid18117 (Box 7, Cassette ref151)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town Speech in Parliament, 1998 September 4; cuid18118 (Box 97, Dvd ref150)
    This video features the first portion of a speech by Fidel Castro to the South African parliament in Cape Town, South Africa. Castro begins speaking around minute 5:00. He begins by offering his support and hope for the creation of a new South Africa led by Nelson Mandela, and commends Mandela for his commitment to justice following the end of the apartheid system. Castro calls for an end to divisions on the basis of race, and encourages South Africa and its political leaders to seek to address problems in economic inequality. He discusses the history of colonialism, which led to slavery and exploitation across the globe, expresses his hope that the new South African government will serve as an example of how to break free from the legacy of that system. Audio quality of this video is poor in places.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:58.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 12, various (including Parliament), 1998 September 4; cuid18119 (Box 69, Cassette ref925, Box 85, Dvd ref925)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:42.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 13, Fidel Speech, 1998 September 4; cuid18120 (Box 69, Cassette ref926, Box 85, Dvd ref926)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban, Fidel Mandela greeting, 1998; cuid18121 (Box 77, Dvd ref152)
    This brief clips shows a greeting in Durban between Nelson Mandela and Fidel Castro. There are two versions, one with music and one without.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:02:32.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban, 1998; cuid18122 (Box 70, Cassette ref922, Box 85, Dvd ref922)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:22:07.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: "Pretoria (part 1) Soweto", 1998; cuid18127 (Box 97, Dvd ref148)
    This video begins with on-the-street interviews in Soweto, South Africa with individuals gathered in anticipation of a visit by Fidel Castro. Interviewees explain why they are excited to see Fidel Castro, and several express their gratitude for Cuba's support of the fight against the apartheid government. The footage then changes to show Castro's arrival. The end of the video provides approximately 10 minutes of a rally honoring Castro. The speakers welcome Cuban and South African leaders and affirm the friendship between the two nations. Speakers also celebrate the memory of the Cuban revolution and Cuba's role in supporting democracy in South Africa.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:52.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 2), 1998 September 2; cuid18123 (Box 97, Dvd ref128)
    This video largely features Nelson and Winnie Mandela greeting world leaders and delegates at the Non-Aligned Movement Summit in Durban, South Africa. Mandela can be seen greeting several prominent individuals including Yasser Arafat and Fidel Castro. At minute 18:04 the video features portions of Mandela's speech, which appears to have been recorded from a television screen or projector. The speech is not complete, but in it, Mandela speaks about the need for developed countries to commit to supporting those that are less developed. He specifically calls for the United Nations to support the people in Angola and Sudan.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:00.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 3), 1998 September 2; cuid18124 (Box 97, Dvd ref129)
    This video begins with footage of Fidel Castro at the Non-Aligned Movement Summit in Durban, South Africa. The first 10 minutes feature Castro greeting other delegates and walking through crowds. At minute 10:32 the footage changes to portions of Castro's speech at the summit, which contains overlapping footage from video ref133. In the speech Castro calls for reforms with the United Nations, International Monetary Fund, and World Bank. He likewise criticizes wealthy nations, the United States in particular, for the proliferation of weapons, destruction of the environment, and the abuses of market capitalism.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:47.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 4) Interviews/Economic Crisis CNN Copy, 1998 September 2; cuid18125 (Box 97, Dvd ref133)
    This video features a speech by Fidel Castro at the Non-Aligned Movement Summit in Durban, South Africa. Castro begins by thanking the leaders of the South African government, and calls for reforms with the United Nations to provide greater representation of countries in Asia, Africa, and Latin America. He specifically calls for an expansion of the Security Council and an end to permanent membership. He likewise criticizes the International Monetary Fund and World Bank, both of which he argues disproportionately benefit wealthy nations, and the United States in particular. In his speech Castro also criticizes wealthy nations development and sales of weapons, lack of respect for the environment, and displacement of people in the third world.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:42.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 5) "Copy El Papa", 1998 September 2; cuid18126 (Box 6, Cassette ref134)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Fidel at Robben Island and Entering Soweto, 1998; cuid18128 (Box 69, Cassette ref927, Box 85, Dvd ref927)
    At Robben Island Estela Bravo interviews South Africans about Fidel Castro. There are scenes of a speech welcoming Castro followed by him talking with people and answering questions. The tape also contains footage in Soweto of Castro's arrival, and shows him placing a wreath on the monument to the 1976 uprising. The sound cuts in and out in several sections.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Soweto (3), 1998; cuid18129 (Box 77, Dvd ref156)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: "Transfers of Omar Chile Order Hope Robben Island", 1998; cuid18130 (Box 7, Cassette ref155)
  - Footage: Nelson Mandela and Fidel Castro, 1998 July 7; cuid18131 (Box 97, Dvd ref1013)
    This video features a series of clips of South African president Nelson Mandela visiting Cuba. The video begins with footage of Mandela arriving in Cuba where he is greeted by Fidel Castro. The bulk features Mandela and Castro at addressing crowds across Cuba, but does not contain any complete speeches. Much of the audio captured in these clips features informal discussions between the two leaders as they travel to different venues. Footage at the end of the video features Fidel Castro during a visit to South Africa, and ends with a segment of footage shot sometime earlier in which Mandela asks Castro to visit South Africa.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:48.
  - Footage: Various, Including Fidel Castro with Compay Segundo and Others, undated; cuid18132 (Box 68, Cassette ref850, Box 83, Dvd ref850)
    Some of the footage shows Fidel Castro at a reception for a group of doctors, which took place on Castro's birthday. There is black and white historical footage and, at the end, a there is footage of Castro with Hugo Chávez during a trip to Venezuela.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:39:21.
  - Footage: At a Reception, includes Fidel, Raúl Castro and Gabriel García Márquez, undated; cuid18133 (Box 77, Dvd ref181)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:06:00.
  - Grenada Footage, 1998 August 1; cuid18134 (Box 70, Cassette ref912, Box 85, Dvd ref912)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:44.
  - Grenada Footage: Fidel "Casa les Ministro", 1998; cuid18135 (Box 70, Cassette ref910, Box 85, Dvd ref910)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:17:44.
  - "Grenada Speech", 1998; cuid18136 (Box 6, Cassette ref99)
  - "Grenada Airport - Fidel", 1998; cuid18137
  - Info Packet, 2001; cuid18138 (Box 72, Folder 5)
  - Jamaica Footage: Lt. Governor Visit, circa 1998; cuid18139 (Box 70, Cassette ref911, Box 85, Dvd ref911)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:50.
  - Jamaica Footage: West Indies University Chancellor, circa 1998; cuid18140 (Box 70, Cassette ref909, Box 85, Dvd ref909)
  - Jamaica Footage: Fidel Speech in Mandela Park, 1998; cuid18141 (Box 97, Dvd ref1005)
    This video features a small portion of a speech by Fidel Castro at a ceremony celebrating the opening of Mandela Park in Kingston, Jamaica in 1998. Castro discusses European tourism, and argues that development of Jamaican tourism does not compete with tourist economies of other Caribbean nations, but rather represents a good sign for Caribbean tourism in general. Castro is then presented with the gift of a book by Jamaican spelling bee champion Jody-Anne Maxwell.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:06:35.
  - "Mandela Park - Patterson", circa 1998; cuid18143 (Box 6, Cassette ref126)
  - Footage: Castro Arriving in Montego Bay, circa 1998; cuid18144 (Box 97, Dvd ref103)
    This video contains footage of Fidel Castro arriving to a celebration in Montego Bay, Jamaica. The bulk of the footage shows crowds of Jamaicans waiting along a street for Castro's motorcade to arrive. It also shows Castro arriving and greeting individuals in the crowd. At the end, a man can be heard off camera addressing welcoming Castro to the city.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:11:39.
  - Castro, Fidel: End of Speech in Mandela Park, Jamaica, circa 1998; cuid18145 (Box 97, Dvd ref106)
    This video features the end of a speech by Fidel Castro in Mandela Park in Kingston, Jamaica. In this portion of the speech Castro discusses the need for Caribbean solidarity as a way to promote education and economic development in the region. He also calls for a greater dedication to the preservation of natural resources, protection of the environment, and support of neighbors after natural disasters such as hurricanes. At the end of the speech Castro is presented with a gift to thank him for visiting the city.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:15:19.
  - "Plaza - Sam Sharpe - Montego Bay", circa 1998; cuid18146 (Box 97, Dvd ref116)
    This video features on-the-street interviews with crowds waiting for the arrival of Fidel Castro. In a series of brief interviews Estela Bravo asks individuals why they have come to see Castro speak and their opinions about him as a leader. Many express their admiration for Castro, specifically citing Cuba's role as a leader in education and healthcare in the Caribbean.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 0:24:54.
  - Crowd Footage: Castro Speech at Sam Sharpe Square in Montego Bay, Jamaica, circa 1998; cuid18147 (Box 97, Dvd ref144)
    This video features footage of crowds in Montego Bay, Jamaica watching a speech by Fidel Castro. The footage focuses predominantly on individuals and their reactions to Castro's speech. Castro speaks in Spanish while his translator speaks in English, but the audio is only present in the background, while the video focuses predominantly on members of the crowd. The video starts and stops several times and as a result does not contain a complete recording of Castro's speech.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:19:59.
  - Grenada; Fidel Hotel Pegaso with Jamaican Governor, circa 1998; cuid18148 (Box 6, Cassette ref125)
  - News footage - Pierre Trudeau, etc., undated; cuid18149 (Box 62, Cassette ref1032)
  - Parts of Interview Translated Into English, 2001; cuid18150 (Box 72, Folder 20-21)
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage - Miami, Little Havana, 1993 July 15, 1993 July 17; cuid18151 (Box 69, Cassette ref886, Box 85, Dvd ref886)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:20.
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, 1993 July 16; cuid18152 (Box 46, Cassette ref1002)
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, includes Lucius Walker, 1993 July 17; cuid18154 (Box 62, Cassette ref1003)
    This tape is potentially damaged or unviewable.
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, 1993 July 16; cuid18155 (Box 9, Cassette ref72)
  - Photos of Rangel, Mandela, Clinton, El Papa, and Hotel Teresa, 1996 August 10; cuid18156 (Box Digitized Access Files, Video ref19)
    This video contains no audio. It features close-up shots of photographs of New York Representative Charles Rangel with people such as Nelson Mandela, President Bill Clinton, and Pope John Paul II. There are various street and building shots in Harlem in New York City, such as at 125th Street and 7th Avenue, the Hotel Theresa, and the the Adam Clayton Powell Jr. State Office Building.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:09:53.
  - Photos of Alicia Alonso, Ramon Castro, Fidel Castro, Leonel Soto, Samora Machel, and Others, circa 1995-2000; cuid18157 (Box 97, Dvd ref74)
    This video features still images of Fidel Castro and an interview with Cuban revolutionary Lionel Soto. The first 10 minutes features shots of still images of Castro with members of his family, including his oldest brother Ramón and his mother Lina Ruz González. Later photos feature Castro speaking to Cuban dancer Alicia Alonso after one of her performances. At minute 10:10 the video changes to an interview with Lionel Soto. Soto speaks about his memories of Castro and the student activist movement at the University of Havana. He describes student activism in period leading up to the Cuban revolution and Castro's role as a leader of that movement.
  - Presenting Fidel Documentary in Los Angeles, circa 2001; TW_TAM_616_ER_8 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_8)
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro Speech (part 1), 2000 September 8; cuid376 (Box 96, Dvd ref1028)
    This video features footage of Fidel Castro's 2000 visit to the Riverside Church in the Harlem. The footage begins with a short speech by Bronx Congressman Jose Serrano welcoming Castro the New York City. The first 14-minutes feature individuals welcoming Castro and the crowd cheering for him and singing "Happy Birthday." At minute 14:30 Castro addresses the crowd and thanks them for their hospitality. He discusses his previous visits to New York City, and talks about several social issues like the blockade against Cuba, and maternal deaths and child malnutrition in the third world.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:18.
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro Speech (part 2), 2000 September 8; cuid377 (Box 96, Dvd ref1029)